Guide to the Mendez Mural Community Garden Archive 1996-2000 MSS.100
Fales Library and Special Collections
Mendez Mural Community Garden Archive
1996-2000
Fales Library and Special Collections
Wright, Jeffery C. (Jeffrey Cyphers)
MSS.100
3 Linear Feet (4 boxes)
The East Village's Mendez Mural Community Garden grew outside of city support but became a fixture in the community and was widely utilized. In 1997, the city decided to sell the land to real-estate developers creating a community uproar and protest. On New Years Eve, 1997 the land was bulldozed for condominiums. The collection documents the struggle to save the garden.
Provenance
The Mendez Mural Community Garden Archive was a gift of Jeff Wright, given to Fales Library in May 2000.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Series II and 2008 Accretion have been digitized, and files are available to view by clicking on links in this finding aid - please click on Series II on the sidebar to see the links. If you are a rights holder and are concerned that you have found material on this website for which you have not granted permission (or is not covered by a copyright exception under US copyright laws), you may request the removal of the material while University Counsel looks into your claim. You can read more about our Take Down Policy here. Please contact the Fales Library and Special Collections, fales.library@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596.
Historical Note
The East Village's Mendez Mural Community Garden(11th Street between Avenues A and B), which had been a vacant lot since the early 1970's, was brought into existence in the early 1990's partly through the work of sculptor, Ken Hiratsuka, and muralist, 'Chico' who brought trees, plants and art to the space. The park grew outside of city support in a neighborhood that had suffered in previous years from drug-crime and violence. It became a fixture in the community and was widely utilized. In 1997, the city exercised their claim of ownership on the land, and when then Mayor Guiliani decided to sell the land to real-estate developers, a community uproar and protest followed. In the end, the bid to save the garden was unsuccessful, and on New Years Eve, 1997 the land was bulldozed for condominiums.
Scope and Content Note
The Mendez Mural Community Garden Archive documents the lawsuit brought by several artists involved in the creation of the Mendez Mural Garden against the Partnership Housing Development Fund Company, Inc. of the City of New York. It also contains articles, correspondence, 'zines, photos, maps, flyers, and posters relating to the Mendez controversy and other battles over garden space on the Lower East Side, dating from 1996 through 2000.
SERIES DESCRIPTION
Series 1: Legal Materials: contains one box of materials relating to the legal case over the Mendez Mural Community Garden, including legal documents and supporting materials such as petitions, photos, and letters of support from the community.
Series 2: Materials relating to Mendez Garden and other Lower East Side garden controversies: contains articles, correspondence, zines, photos, maps, flyers and posters relating to the Mendez controversy and other battles over garden space on the Lower East Side, dating from 1996 through 2000. Folders 9-9d contain miscellaneous materials removed from their original non-archival 3-ring binders; they have been stored in their original order.
Accretions 2008: includes material related to Jeffrey Wright's community garden activism from 1997-2000. The bulk of material pertains to the activity and events of the 11th Street Garden (Chico West). Photographs, legal documents, press clippings, and other records are contained within this accretion.
Arrangement
Materials are organized by subject and document type.
The files are grouped into two series.
Missing Title
Series I: Legal Materials
Series II: Mendez Garden and Other Lower East Side Garden Controversies
Separated Material
There is no information about materials that are associated by provenance to the described materials that have been physically separated or removed.
Petitions.; Clippings (information artifacts); Urban renewal -- Citizen participation.; Lower East Side (New York, N.Y.); Vacant lands.; Mendez Mural Community Garden (New York, N.Y.); Community development, Urban; Briefs (legal documents); Community gardens |z New York (State) |z New York.; Fliers (printed matter); Photographs.; Chico; Hiratsuka, Ken
- Series I: Legal Materials
  - Form letters sent, undated; 31142040617196 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Form letters sent, have ribbons, undated; 31142040617196 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Original letters, ribbons done, undated; 31142040617196 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Copies of postcard backs, undated; 31142040617196 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Copies of postcard backs, cont'd., undated; 31142040617196 (Box 1, Folder 4a.)
  - Petitions, undated; 31142040617196 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Legal statements, info re: Mendez Garden, undated; 31142040617196 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Legal photos, undated; 31142040617196 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Trial documents, undated; 31142040617196 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Trial documents, cont'd., undated; 31142040617196 (Box 1, Folder 8a.)
  - Trial documents, cont'd., undated; 31142040617196 (Box 1, Folder 8b.)
  - Trial documents, cont'd., undated; 31142040617196 (Box 1, Folder 8c.)
  - Trial documents, cont'd., undated; 31142040617196 (Box 1, Folder 8d.)
  - Trial documents, cont'd., undated; 31142040617196 (Box 1, Folder 8e.)
  - Trial documents, cont'd., undated; 31142040617196 (Box 1, Folder 8f.)
- Series II: Mendez Garden and other Lower East Side garden controversies
  Conditions Governing Access
  Series II has been digitized and files are available to view by clicking on links. If you are a rights holder and are concerned that you have found material on this website for which you have not granted permission (or is not covered by a copyright exception under US copyright laws), you may request the removal of the material while University Counsel looks into your claim. You can read more about our Take Down Policy
  - Letters about uses of public space for gardens (some relating to legal case), undated; 31142040617204 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Garden monographs & zines, undated; 31142040617204 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Photos & slides: general, undated; 31142040617204 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Garden maps & government documents, undated; 31142040617204 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Press packets, undated; 31142040617204 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Press tearsheets, undated; 31142040617204 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Press tearsheets cont'd., undated; 31142040617204 (Box 2, Folder 6a.)
  - Flyers & announcements, undated; 31142040617204 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Internet information, undated; 31142040617204 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Materials previously contained in 3-ring binders (binder 1)-Binders contained articles, correspondence, flyers, photos, and other printed materials relating to the Mendez garden and other garden controversies; these materials have been kept in their original order., undated; 31142040617204 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Materials previously contained in 3-ring binders (binder 1 cont'd.), undated; 31142040617204 (Box 2, Folder 9a.)
  - Materials previously contained in 3-ring binders (binder 1 cont'd.), undated; 31142040617204 (Box 2, Folder 9b.)
  - Materials previously contained in 3-ring binders (binder 2), undated; 31142040617204 (Box 2, Folder 9c.)
  - Materials previously contained in 3-ring binders (binder 2 cont'd.), undated; 31142040617204 (Box 2, Folder 9d.)
  - Printed ephemera, undated; 31142040617204 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Newspapers re: N.Y.C., undated (Box 3 (flat), Folder 11)
  - Posters, undated (Box 3 (flat), Folder 12)
- 2008 Accretion
  - Community gardens, 1997-2000 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Community gardens, 1999-2000 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Community gardens, 1999-2000 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Community gardens, 1999-2000 (Box 3, Folder 4)